A Guide to the Papers of Rockwell Kent, 1914-1921
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Rockwell Kent 1914-1921
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6335-a
This collection consists of 20 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased on [19 Nov 1964] 24 Nov 1964.
Scope and Content Information
Kent's letters discuss World War I, and the characteristics of the British and German people; and mention the German Relief Fund, suspicions that Kent is a German spy and that the police are intercepting his mail. He also discusses life in Newfoundland, money owed, and financial hardship; Impressionism, Cubism, and Futurism; and the sale of his paintings by Ewing and Chappell; and comments on the 1915 Matisse show and the Rand School.
Four photographs of Kent and his home in Brigus, Newfoundland, and a sketch of the St. John's harbor are included.
Correspondents include Charles Daniel and Mrs. Gilchrist.
Contents List
- Letters
  - Rockwell Kent to Mr. [Charles] Daniel 1914 Apr 20, ALS. w/env. 2 p.
    [Mentions picture for Mr. Putnam, work on remodeling house, and requests $15 owed him by C. D.]
  - R. K. to C. D. 1914 May 22, ALS. w/env. 2 p.
    [Thanks for Times supplement. Has sent painting for Putnam. Complains about not receiving money owed.]
  - R. K. to C. D. 1914 Jun 3, ALS. w/env. 2 p.
    [Discusses his painting; is greatly stimulated by the Newfoundland area and people.]
  - R. K. to C. D. 1914 Jun 20, ALS. w/env. 2 p.
    [Mentions C. D.'s trip abroad and writes of his life in Newfoundland.]
  - R. K. to C. D. 1914 Sep 7, ALS. w/env. 2 p.
    [Discusses his problem with the police in Brigus which appears to stem from his speaking of his German sympathies.]
  - R. K. to C. D. 1914 Sep 11, ALS. w/env. 2 p.
    [Discusses the war, and the British vs. the German people.]
  - R. K. to C. D. 1914 Oct 7, ALS. w/env. 3 p.
    [Discusses his thoughts on truth, emotions, life and art. Mentions Stieglitz, Hartley, Putnam, and Ruggles.]
  - R. K. to C. D. 1914 Oct 21, ALS. w/env. 1 p.
    [Indicates he will send a picture for the December exhibition. Mentions he has had tonsillitis.]
  - R. K. to C. D. 1914 Oct 26, ALS. 1 p.
    [Requests address of Henry Mielke who is in charge of receiving contributions for the German relief fund.]
  - R. K. to C. D. 1914 Nov 2, ALS. w/env. 2 p.
    [Requests an advance of money; is behind in paying bills. Suspects the police are holding up his letters.]
  - R. K. to C. D. 1914 Nov 28, ALS. w/env. 2 p.
    [Has shipped the picture from St. Johns for his exhibition. Some people in Brigus think he is making maps for Germany and is a spy. Discusses his working conditions. Includes sketch of St. John's harbor.]
  - R. K. to C. D. 1915 Jan 8, ALS. w/env. 4 p.
    [Discusses his problems with getting his paintings through customs. Asks C. D. to deliver enclosed letter to congressman concerning the problem.]
  - R. K. to C. D. 1915 Jan 8, ALS. 3 p.
    [In same envelope as above.] [Outlines his case against local officials who threaten to seize and detain his paintings. Requests help from U. S.]
  - R. K. to C. D. 1915 Jan 12, ALS. w/env. 2 p.
    [Discusses sale of his drawings by Mr. Chappell of Ewing and Chappell, and payment for same. Suspects the police are reading his mail.]
  - R. K. to C. D. 1915 Jan 17, ALS. w/env. 2 p.
    [Has received catalog and requests copies of the half tone of his painting.]
  - R. K. to C. D. 1915 Mar, ALS. [w/env dated 1915 Mar 24]2 p.
    [Comments on the catalog of the Matisse show and the asinine argument printed therein. Mentions his own work. Discusses Impressionism, and its relationship to Cubism and Futurism.]
- Photographs
  Four photographs, 8 x 13 cm., mentioned in letter of 1914 Apr 20 to C. D.
  - R. K. with a child (probably his daughter) n.d.
  - R. K.'s home in Brigus, Newfoundland n.d.
  - Two views from home across water to hills. n.d.